welcome to meditating with genre Reiki
we live stream every morning at 9:30
a.m. every weekday morning at 9:30 a.m.
we will not be meeting tomorrow because
it is a holiday candidate Mondays we
alternate between a pie a day which is I
do the entire ecology of practices so
that we've learned so far and and the
following Monday would be Dharma day in
which we in which I teach a new lesson a
new principle of practice that builds on
previous principles or practices for
those of you who are joining us for the
first time please go into the notes and
you'll see links to previous lessons and
sets I recommend doing lesson one I
think this these I'm sorry about that
I recommend doing lesson one right away
and then you can continue meeting with
us and then every Saturday to Sunday
doing another of the following lessons
and you'll very soon catch up with us
please like the stream to increase its
visibility in the YouTube algorithm at
the end of every set we have Q&A please
limit your questions to this ecology
practices this course we're on but you
can ask questions from any of the
lessons that have been taught for it
even any of the answers that I've given
to other people for more general
questions please come to the general Q&A
leave the livestream on YouTube every
third Friday of the month at 3 p.m.
Eastern time and that will be July 17th
this month I think that's everything for
now so please get yourself into position
set your phones on do not disturb and we
will begin when I say begin begin
you
[Music]
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best she can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness cognition character and
communitas perhaps by reciting the five
promises to yourself
and
okay so we have some time for some
questions just waiting for them to come
up on the screen
so the first is from Andy Hema struttin
which I promise to come back and a treat
in depth which I would like to do now is
I think this is a very important
question
Andy writes I'm not sure was because of
my ADH East it stimulation stimulant
medication I had a weird scary psychosis
like experience have you got any insight
and I'm really mind as I want to carry
on started well meditating and carried
on for like a half an hour but where
they have felt really present after at
all weird experience from the next
couple of sips I felt paranoid but I
just labeled it and it somewhat went
away after okay so the first thing we
should note is that all of these
practices have potential negative side
effects as I mentioned the meditation
practices can have these generate weird
experiences where you hear your name
called hours flash of light or electric
shock right the cheap practices there's
I mean this is typically for people who
practice it very excessively theirs was
achieved syndrome where people's
psychophysical interact integration goes
askew so part of the reason why I teach
you an ecology of practices is not the
sole reason by any means but there's a
therapeutic reason which is by having
multiple different practices they act as
checks and balances and you don't get to
I think the right word is over committed
to any particular practice so it's very
important to try and first of all engage
in the entire ecology on practices again
I don't mean I don't mean that
everything I teach you should have
mastery but you should have an ecology
of practice meditative alright
contemplative
AG Kong practice and some of the other
practices that we're going to idea so
it's very important to pursue an ecology
of practice it's very important to do
what you did Andy which was to share
what's happening to you what you did
with the Sangha and you get a lot of
people reporting and that this isn't
that aberrant an experience all of that
so that's just the general thing to do
everybody if you get these abnormal
experiences in which you may feel he
personalized or he realized very
important to share them to talk about
them to make sure that right you you can
have a sense of cultivating mindfulness
outside of so let's say it's invokana
like do meta and oh this is how I can
cultivate this and I'm not getting the
same experience there so all of that is
very important
next this is also very important I don't
know you and so if this is a persistent
pattern with you I would recommend that
you ameliorate this the practice
significantly reduce how deep you're
doing it hour long year sitting and that
you seek out professional therapeutic
intervention if on the other hand and
this is what seems to be happening as
you immerse yourself in annek the
dynamic ecology of practices and in the
living Sangha and as you continue on
with the practice if you find it's
ameliorating then that's generally a
good sign that you should keep going but
and again I can't teach you everything
at once and again I there's lots of
stuff to go so I'm going to do a bit of
for shutting we're going to do this more
in depth when we're doing the wisdom
Hypatia and we we do this section on
stoicism but we need to cultivate
practices that help with the
self-deception around how our beliefs
are formed and and get intervene on
certain ways in which
thinking can sort of spin off so I'm
going to recommend first of all three
one of three books so you can get all
three books if you want here's the first
book biased
I'll cognitive biases in Tarot judgment
here's the next book the 25 cognitive
biases and then here's the third book
cognitive biases a popular guide because
what I'm going to recommend for for all
of us but also for you in particular
Andy is to cultivate what's called
active open mindedness I could open
mindedness and like I said when we go
into the wisdom our patient will come at
this in more depth this is a preliminary
introduction octave open mindedness is
practice every morning read about one of
these biases think about it try to
remember instances in your life where
you encountered one of these values and
then throughout the day try to create a
reminder I can I see my frog of my stone
or something else I check and see mmm
it's the biota bite has the bias has
been recently present in my thinking is
the president right now try to catch
yourself spontaneously through the day I
go oh there's the confirmation bias
oh that's the availability on us and
then actively counteracted and then at
the end of the day recorded in your
journal if you noted or remember and
don't beat yourself up if you don't it's
a very very gradual process it's very
gradual process but try to note any bias
is if you cultivate rationality which
isn't doesn't mean being logical it's
this ability to detect the way our
thinking can fall into patterns of
self-deception that can also help
ameliorate the tendency for these
abnormal experiences to permeate and
drive the kind of rumination that can be
dissociative and can enhance a sense of
delusion so those are the things I would
recommend in general really when you're
when these things are happening if it's
not ameliorating and you need to then
you need to seriously
the depth and the duration of the
practice maybe even stop it completely
and get some professional help
therapeutic intervention if there's a
sense that it is ameliorating with the
practice then really dive into the
ecology of practices don't get don't do
just one practice do a multiple do the
ecology practices and scent sensitive
dynamic capacity for self correction
everybody should share I mentioned this
we should share our we should celebrate
our are moments when we realize the
Buddha we should also celebrate our
aberrant experiences not because we can
offer therapy to each other we are not
professionally trained but we can in a
sense resituated and other people say
yes I've had that experience without it
it takes a lot of the numinous edge off
these experiences to realize that they
are shared with others so the living
Sangha is also a very powerful resource
and then like I said begin to cultivate
active open mindedness because it
seriously challenges our tendency to get
into very biased self-deceptive thought
around these aberrant experiences when
they occur so I hope that was helpful in
d-tackle in Soho said what do I do about
inches well see if you can apply the
five factors including mine well this up
to the point where the principal does
one of the primary principles takes
place if you can honestly say and I'm
not inside your head I don't know if you
can honestly say I'm not this is
becoming such an overwhelming experience
I can't learn anything from it all I'm
doing is merely enduring it and break
the practice and scratch your itch
pay attention monthly to what's
happening as you do so if you can do one
other thing though before when you come
out of it and there's an itch and when
you when you started engaging the act of
reducing the itch does the itch start to
immediately disappear even before you
scratch because then take note of that
because then
so now they're very clever weighing the
impish monkey mind has figured out how
to distract you and get you involved and
get you out of state okay yeah monkey
mind is not your enemy and monkey mind
is not your enemy okay so if you can
know because that means right that again
it's much more and there's nothing
there's nothing abnormal or stigmatic
about this right but that's a that's
another way in which your monkey mind is
sort of distracting is distracting you
it's a bit sort of psychosomatic and
that's what's so the basic principle
with itches are trying to apply the five
factors of important mindfulness if it
goes away
don't get all celebratory just about
your breath I'm if you get to the point
where you're just enduring as a start
mindfully scratch but see what have to
see what happens even before you scratch
is the itch ameliorating because that
tells you that it's it's way in which
you're building up a habit of
distraction
okay so just paper go ahead and scratch
but note that pay attention to it maybe
maybe you won't even need to scratch it
all and then go back on to City OS teen
service then sometimes when I get a
feeling of are my head tends to tilt
should I let it tilt a hold it back
thank you ah sorry oh that was a pun
haha there was a performative punishes
that it ah yes that's a good question
because I think if the experience is
happening spontaneously
and you are not identifying the practice
with achieving ah then letting your body
do what it needs to do in order to
unfold that experience is probably the
right thing to do
eunbi I hope he sends my caution because
these special experiences can we can
very quickly equally even if we don't
sort of consciously say to ourselves say
ah that's the point of this practice the
point of this practice is it is my own
personal ah induction machine right dad
so that's a worry and a concern because
while ah is relevant to the cultivation
of wisdom pursued exclusively it will be
detrimental to the cultivation of wisdom
like anything else pursued exclusively
so as long as it's arising spontaneously
and you do not get disappointed this is
the mark if you have a sit and you don't
have that are you disappointed do you
feel like oh oh oh then I would
recommend trying to let the eye
experiences go but if that's not the
case and you're happy to let them come
and go you're not disappointed where
they don't come and when they do come
let your head tilt back and let it
unfold as much as it can but but try to
not go too far because you're going to
start to uproot yourself so we do the
head lift in some of the cheek tongue
practices because it actually does
redirect brain activity James Austin has
shown this in some of his work and so if
your brain is trying to read organize
its activity and that is leading to
right it's exacting sort of visual
processing to do that then let it occur
so I hope that answered your question
then Gao welcome Ben sometimes my deep
impostor feels like falling asleep not
literally as I'm sitting erect with my
head up but they still must feel
sluggish empty and boring so that is you
are falling asleep and so that is where
it's very important to energize and
activate the five factors of inquiring
mindfulness doctor bring
right that deep sense of questing
exploration moving deeper even in the
stillness I know this sounds like a
contradiction but this is this is the
movement appropriate to Eternity even in
the stillness there's a motion that
right and I know that sounds like a
contradiction but there's a motion in
the sense that there is a depth to the
stillness that you can disclose and so
the five factors of acquiring
mindfulness should be deliberately
enhanced if you're getting that sense of
sluggish sluggishness so very good
question then I hope that that was a
helpful answer so everyone I'll hold
these books up again one more time again
it's down the road when we get into the
wisdom of a pichia you're going to want
one of these or perhaps all three
thank you everyone for joining the sign
that means a great deal to me and I I
thank you all for it I want to thank my
dear friend and a techno major Maura
who's making everything happen my
beloved son Jason who is assigned behind
the scenes making everything that needs
to be done coping with the contingencies
he's always there for me
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video on on that
channel you'll find links to the lecture
series awakening from the meaning crisis
and the dialogo series voices with verve
a key I will be appearing tonight 6:00
p.m. Eastern Time on Peter Lindbergh
thus Noah with died sense talk and we'll
be going through the DIA logos practice
for those of you are interested so on my
channel you will find as I said these
two resources these two series which
will help explore a lot of the themes we
talked about here and we're trying to
practice in depth and set them and
situate them with a more on it within a
more encompassing framework and way of
life
please invite others who might benefit
by sharing this series try to help as
many people as I possibly can
fred is here pleasure of doubt and I
strongly recommend you go you if you can
join the did go into the discord discord
server right now there's links and the
description you'll find people who have
a group of people who have just done
this set many of them all have already
done she come practices they usually do
some Lexy oh there's like I said there's
in-depth discussion of these broader
issues I'm strongly recommend getting
involved with the disparate server I'm
there every second Monday at 6 p.m. for
general QA and many of the people that
appear on voices with for baekje will
also be there for general Q&A we're
doing this every weekday morning not
tomorrow tomorrow's Canada Day holiday
they're not doing
tomorrow but we'll do this every weekday
morning at 9:30 Eastern Time
please remember that continuity of
practice is more important than sure
quantity of practice and there's no
enemy worse than your own mind and body
there's no friend no ally no two
companion on the path better than your
own mind and body be lamps unto
yourselves and to each other take care
everyone I'll see you on Thursday okay